[Music]
Reedman reads
The Giver by Lois Lowry, narrated by Fraser Reedman.
Chapter 22.
Now the landscape was changing.. It was a subtle change,, hard to identify at
first.. The road was narrower, and bumpy,, apparently no longer tended by road
crews.. It was harder, suddenly, to balance on the bike, as the front wheel wobbled
over stones and ruts.. One night, Jonas fell, when the bike jolted to a sudden
stop against a rock.. He grabbed instinctively for Gabriel;, and the new
child, strapped tightly in his seat,, was uninjured,, only frightened when the bike
fell to its side.. But Jonas's ankle was twisted, and his knees were scraped and
raw,, blood seeping through his torn trousers.. Painfully he rided himself and
the bike, and reassured Gabe.. Tentatively he began to ride in daylight.. He had
forgotten the fear of the searchers, who seemed to have diminished into the past..
But now there were new fears;. the unfamiliar landscape held hidden, unknown
perils.. Trees became more numerous,, and the forests beside the road were dark
and thick with mystery.. They saw streams more frequently now and stopped often to drink..
Jonas carefully washed his injured knees,, wincing as he rubbed at the raw
flesh.. The constant ache of his swollen ankle was eased when he soaked it
occasionally in the cold water that rushed through roadside gullies.. He was
newly aware that Gabriel's safety depended entirely upon his own continued
strength.. They saw their first waterfall, and for the first time wildlife.. "Plane!,
Plane!", Gabriel called,, and Jonas turned swiftly into the trees,. though he had
not seen planes in days,, and he did not hear an aircraft engine now.. When he
stopped the bicycle in the shrubbery and turned to grab Gabe,, he saw the small
chubby arm pointing toward the sky..
Terrified,, he looked up,, but it was not a plane at all..
Though he had never seen one before,, he identified it from his fading memories,,
for The Giver had given them to him often.. It was a bird.. Soon there were
many birds along the way,, soaring overhead,, calling., They saw deer;, and
once, beside the road,, looking at them, curious and unafraid,, a small reddish
brown creature with a thick tail,, whose name Jonas did not know.. He slowed the
bike and they stared at one another until the creature turned away and
disappeared into the woods.. All of it was new to him.. After a life of Sameness
and predictability,, he was awed by the surprises that lay beyond each curb of
the road.. He slowed the bike again and again to look with wonder at wild
flowers, to enjoy the throaty warble of a new bird nearby,, or merely to watch
the way wind shifted the leaves in the trees.. During his 12 years in the
community,, he had never felt such simple moments of exquisite happiness..
But there were desperate fears building in him now as well.. The most relentless
of his new fears was that they would starve. Now that they had left the
cultivated fields behind them,. it was almost impossible to find food.. They
finished the meager store of potatoes and carrots they had saved from the last
agricultural area,, and now they were always hungry.. Jonas knelt by a stream
and tried without success to catch a fish with his hands.. Frustrated,, he
threw rocks into the water,, knowing even as he did so that it was useless..
Finally,, in desperation,, he fashioned a makeshift net,, looping the strands of
Gabriel's blanket around a curved stick..
After countless tries,, the net yielded two flopping silvery fish.. Methodically,
Jonas hacked them to pieces with a sharp rock and fed the raw shreds to himself
and to Gabriel.. They ate some berries, and tried without success to catch a
bird.. At night,, while Gabriel slept beside him,, Jonas lay awake,, tortured by
hunger,, and remembered his life in the community, where meals were delivered to
each dwelling every day.. He tried to use the flagging power of his memory to
recreate meals,, and managed brief, tantalizing fragments, banquetss with
huge roasted meats;, birthday parties with thick frosted cakes;, and lush
fruits picked and eaten, sunwormed and dripping, from trees.. But when the memory
glimpses subsided,, he was left with the gnawing,, painful
emptiness.. Jonas remembered, suddenly and grimly, the time in his childhood when he
had been chastised for misusing a word..
The word had been "starving.". "You have never been starving,," he had been told..
"You will never be starving.." Now he was.. If he had stayed in the community,,
he would not be.. It was as simple as that..
Once he had yearned for choice..
Then, when he had had a choice,, he had made the wrong one:. the choice to leave..
And now he was starving..
But if he had stayed..., His thoughts continued.. If he had stayed,, he would
have starved in other ways.. He would have lived a life hungry for feelings,,
for color,, for love..
And Gabriel?. For Gabriel, there would have been no life at all., So there had
not really been a choice.. It became a struggle to ride the bicycle as Jonas
weakened from lack of food, and realized at the same time that he was
encountering something he had for a long time yearned to see: hills.. His sprained
ankle throbbed as he forced the pedal downward at an effort that was almost
beyond him., And the weather was changing.. It rained for 2 days.. Jonas
had never seen rain,, though he had experienced it often in the memories.. He
had liked those rains,, enjoyed the new feeling of it,, but this was different..
He and Gabriel became cold and wet,, and it was hard to get dry,, even when
sunshine occasionally followed.. Gabriel had not cried during the long, frightening journey..
Now he did.. He cried because he was hungry and cold and terribly weak.. Jonas
cried,, too,, for the same reasons,. and another reason as well., He wept because
he was afraid now that he could not save Gabriel..
He no longer cared about himself.
[Music]